[SPEAKER_01]: I think you're probably going to revolve around the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I thought we can start... Obviously, it's translated differently, and without getting into that.
[SPEAKER_01]: We usually regard it as assumption, because in its nature you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it implies me reacting to things in a certain appropriative manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: But upādāna is what precedes that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You appropriating things in Rīgāriyāma's mind is the result of the upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not your upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you can't... it's not on the level of choice for you to stop clinging.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why whenever you say clinging or grasping, well, at least for me, it kind of sounds like, oh, I'm clinging to this and I'm grasping that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already the result of upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what means it's more of an assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: You took something for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: You took for granted that you can own this and now you're exercising your attitude and actions towards ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will never do that if you fully understand that it's unownable to begin with, if you free yourself from that assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if we take assumption then, for the contemplation, what would be... how would you describe its properties?
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, well, it's practically... sensuality is an assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you describe that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it an assumption?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, for me, assumptions about, like, something that's unexamined, they kind of underlies everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I guess, in terms of sensuality, it would be
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is not understanding, not seeing, not examining.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: What sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is it then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have... you arrive at assumption through the example of that which being assumed, in this case, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is sensuality then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Your kind of attitude towards things that you can bodily...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, like, again, let's try and be more accurate in a sense of the tone.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no need for a theoretical answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: More like, imagine you, in the experience of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: Describe that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a form of pull.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you have sensuality, for example, without a desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, to be honest, I think karma comes from the verb karmēti, which means desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sense desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot possibly engage in any experience of centrality, let's still call it centrality, without having a desire underlying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the assumption of centrality must be on that level as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that level of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as we described before, centrality means a perverting order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Upādāna means perverting order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Owning the unownable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming the sense of self outside of this experience as a whole, which is a contradiction in terms, because you're experiencing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you maintaining an assumption whereby you think you can think outside of the experience as a whole, that's why it's an assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it cannot be done
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you not clarifying that it cannot be done, you keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the desire, being also another type of upādāna, shares the same nature, or must be sharing the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't it because desire basically involves this given situation?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, this, this basically, like, so, I, sitting here, not having this taste, but with that taste as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's make it even more narrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you have desire if things are unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a desire for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, is then the pleasure also basis for your desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure for... wanting pleasure is the basis for the design.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you be wanting pleasure, unless that's already felt pleasantly?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you know it's pleasant, unless you're feeling it pleasantly?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I wanted to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: That basically, the possibility of pleasure is given to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically, I have been subjected to this
[SPEAKER_00]: This possibility for pleasure, not seeing that that possibility for pleasure is just something else that I've been subjected to, I think, let's go for...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to go for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how is that possibility of pleasure felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: That possibility of... well, it depends.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's not recognized as something that I've just been subjected to, then it'll be felt as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you see that it's just yet another thing that I've been subjected to,
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like this lack of that... this feeling I have, not having that thing, whether I'm subjected to that feeling or that feeling, it's all just...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think if you recognize it on the level of... on that level of it's all just something that I have been hit with, then...
[SPEAKER_01]: You see the pain of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm not talking about like, oh, when you made the effort to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the experience of the arisen prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: How's that felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience of the arisen prospect of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensual pleasure, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so you're not engaging, your senses are not engaging with particular pleasure, but now there is a possibility for them to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How's that felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's felt pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, actually, no, it's felt as painful, in the sense that I'm, I want, I need to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's a pleasure involved in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But which, which is the one that comes first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the one that comes first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as it's always important to... That's the thing, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends how you see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you, if you don't recognize
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it doesn't depend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as I explained about the upādāna of Atavāda, for example, it doesn't depend how you see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You always keep assuming your sense of self outside of the experience as a whole, outside of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you see it or not, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you start seeing it, you undo it, and then there is no other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't assume it again, because now you saw it as impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sense-desire shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what we're trying to get to the bottom of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is that nature contained?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what was the question again?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which is... which is that which comes first in the case of arisen prospect of sensual desire, or rather sensual pursuit, sensual pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it that it's unpleasant first,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then prospect of pleasure comes over it, or prospect of pleasure is first, but then that's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, let's back to the practical example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go back to... You have now possibility for a pleasant taste to eat something.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is that felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess, like, ordinarily, it would be pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now when you start thinking about it... Now when you start thinking about it, you realize that, well, there's a pain involved in not having it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And which is... that comes first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it the pain or the ordinary...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is more fundamental, is the pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the most... more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pain is more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The absence of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The absence of pleasure, right now, is... that is... that's more fundamental than the initial kind of buzz you get from the possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the absence of this possible pleasure, this particular food, is first felt unpleasantly, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be the necessary basis, then, for you to go for that pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: To not see that pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: To cover over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, to cover over it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that way, any form of engagement of sense desires requires you to ignore how you feel first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of the fundamental feeling, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pathway of following the sense desire is always open.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing blocking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is that that's felt unpleasantly first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you ignore it, in order to go down that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I say it's like... it's... you're saying it's first felt as unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I say it's like it's more... the more general feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean first felt as in that when you chase the pleasure, the pain disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is... there is a pleasure...
[SPEAKER_01]: The pain remains throughout, which is why the pain is the motivation of your sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like there's a pleasure...
[SPEAKER_00]: This buzz of the possibility of having that taste, but that pleasure is contained within this more general displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what you keep talking about more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more fundamental discomfort of the prospect of pleasure remains throughout your engagement with the pleasure, which is why you keep engaging with the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not being mindful would help you to ignore that
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no starting point for the ignorance in regard to anything, including sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because there is no starting point of this type of ignoring, people... there is also no starting point for their assumption that prospect of pleasure is the pleasure that they already delight in, that they engage with, that they pursue, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they don't see the underlying pain that's constantly present with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously, to the same extent, but on a more fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, through your own engagement with sensuality, you keep obscuring more and more that which underlines it, which is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why sensuality is insatiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because pain is here, on one level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your act towards sensuality alone can be on the domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot do anything about the fact that it's felt painfully before you act.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, no amount of action, satisfaction, desire, proliferation, the extent of your sensual preferences... No amount of restraint would then automatically... Obviously, restraint is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you understand it, you won't be free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, sensuality is not engagement with the objects of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality is assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, there is some perversion of the order there, that's why sensuality is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that perversion is maintained through your engagement based on that ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Engagement with sense-objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, once you remove the ignorance, then engagement with sense-objects cannot induce sensuality anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that obviously means that the extent of your old engagement that was based on ignorance will be significantly reduced.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as, arahant cannot possibly have sexual integrals.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, let's make it even more accurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: If sensualities first felt unpleasantly, don't think about the prospect of the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since we revealed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: How...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not having this thing that I could have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any nature of painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are its characteristics?
[SPEAKER_01]: Painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or what are the characteristics of the experience as a whole that is subjected to a painful feeling that endures?
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's something that you subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can only discover that pain as already enjoying.
[SPEAKER_00]: What else do you discover?
[SPEAKER_00]: I have no control over it being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the natural response?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the ordinary response would be, if you were to not understand that that pain isn't yours, the ordinary response is to say, I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what would be a non-anāgāmī response?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not wanting pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's undesirable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's only because you're not recognizing that it's got... Yeah, no, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's just stick with the pain, because it's basically undesirable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as the Buddha said, in every painful feeling, there is craving to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you're completely free from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how is that prospect of getting rid of pain felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're subjected to pain and there is a possibility of pain ceasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ceasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the possibility of that pain not being there is felt pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Felt pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the pleasure of that prospect?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're on a thread here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is then the pleasure in that prospect?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is pleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Of that pain not being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the pleasure
[SPEAKER_01]: of the prospect of not having this pain is pleasant to the extent that this is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a separate pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a back of the same coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's one phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's another way of looking at the... it's the one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one phenomenon there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because every presence of this implies the absence of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever that is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, presence of pain implies absence of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: This same pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of pain is felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneous to that, the possibility of its absence is felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just an episode of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that pain and that possibility of pleasure
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they separate?
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely bound up with each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you look at one, yeah, you can say that's what I'm feeling, but if you look at the other, but again, from where do they come from?
[SPEAKER_01]: They come from the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you've been struck by that feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically one phenomena with two sides.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like two sides of one coin, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't have one without having the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's on that level that sensuality happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: The assumption of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you...
[SPEAKER_00]: The wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: You put the negative first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you put the pleasure first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a completely gratuitous assumption that's almost like developed for the purpose of kind of covering it up, covering the issues up, a defense mechanism, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that's always the principle of every upādāna, by the way, avoiding pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you develop assumptions, because they shelter you from admitting that you are subject to pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can go into the other upādānas as well, and you'll see it's going to be the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like sīlabhāti paramāsa, my virtue, my duty, not my responsibility to make it my virtue, my duty.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can we stay in this situation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just, I'm just dropping this in, so you can connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But let's go back to the thread that we said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the two sides of the same coin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I just say, so it would be the same if there's a pleasant feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize the lack of that pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which would be painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you assume that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... You put the possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: But generally, one would emphasize the pleasure and ignore... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, like, again, imagine practically you're subjected to some sensual pleasure right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes effort for you to not crave for more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes effort for you to go against the grain and stay and appreciate what you have and enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't make the effort, the mind wants more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because more pleasure means this is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of pain is more pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You put that absence of pain first.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the basis, within the container of that it's painful first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why... that's why we started by asking in general what is first in case of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always... that is its container.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is its fundamental purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize that no amount of engagement with sensuality, as I said, doesn't matter how far down the senses you go, the motivation, the actual pleasure that you feel, on account of sensual engagement, is the pleasure of avoiding pain that's still with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the pleasure of you touching things, tasting things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the pleasure were contained in touch, taste, smell, sight,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would always be pleasant to the same extent, and you wouldn't even... well, you wouldn't be able to think about it, to be honest, because not having... that means... non-engagement means absence of pleasure, absence of possibility of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that sometimes you can eat same things and not experience pleasure on account of it, then eat... eat same things they used to... didn't cause you pleasure, now they're giving you pleasure, means pleasure is not in the sense objects, nor in the sense domain, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, of course, the Buddha said that many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, once you remove desire and lust from your mind, he said even Tathāgata... For Tathāgata, there are beautiful things in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: He sees this is beautiful, this is ugly, this is agreeable, this is disagreeable, but there's absolutely no sensuality whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for most people, when you think, you think sensuality means
[SPEAKER_01]: The the the agreeability of the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality means perversion of your perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: An assumption, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You perceive second to come first, and that which is actually still there is first, you kind of perceive as second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And from that point of view, you realize how sensuality is not linear at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because usually it's like the mind would, once it's subjected to that assumption,
[SPEAKER_01]: And acts out of the assumption would think, I have a desire, then I act, then I fulfill my desire through engaging with this particular sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it's done.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole thing is within the painful container of being subjected to it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is your sole motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the important precision here is, whenever there is a prospect of pleasure that's felt pleasantly, because you'll be avoiding pain, that pleasure is the pleasure of the pain that you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you should learn to see sensuality, sense desires... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as... ...as
[SPEAKER_01]: Now that you brought it up, the Buddha will always say he understands, the one who is free from sensuality, understands gratification, the danger and the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means full understanding of the phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is then the gratification of the sensual assumption?
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: The gratification... well, the extent of the pleasure that you can possibly... that is contained within that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: The extent of the pleasure that's contained with the pain, I mean, that extent would be quite infinite.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because it's all within more general pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a pleasure there, a more particular pleasure, which is what you're putting first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, what somebody, you know, somebody who's bound by sensuality, puts first, this pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not seeing that that's bound up by a more fundamental pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but what is gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: That pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how... the extent to which that can... the way...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the gratification, then, is absence of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: The gratification is absence of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not absence of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because it's a pain... there's a pleasure there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you have this prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's put it like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is that gratification?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody can chip in, by the way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it the ignoring of the pain?
[SPEAKER_03]: The blindness to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignoring of the pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well... Is pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, more, more precisely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, we are not trying to undo the gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're just trying to clarify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the pleasure that arises on...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's stop there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pleasure that arises on account of possibility of sense objects, which are, yeah, all of it is underlined by the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is that pleasure pleasant, as I asked before, as we clarified before?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you feeling that prospect pleasantly?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's... because you're emphasizing...
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you crave getting rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, that's the gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delighting in the prospect of getting rid of the pain that you don't question.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't question your attitude towards the originally, fundamentally, presently enduring pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't question it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, there are prospects to then, like, get away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will then automatically delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gratification is the delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your delight in the sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the gratification of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not engagement with the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you can get everything you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's you delighting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already when you start satisfying your desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you accept the possibility of satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, satisfaction over there, means escaping this presently enduring pain over here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on that level, certainly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not be explicitly thinking, like, clarifying, oh, it's a hope, but yeah, it's on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the possibility of satisfaction... ...is already delighted in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already... that delight in the possibility of satisfaction is where gratification already is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, then the danger is mixed in, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you go down the domain that has nothing to do with why you are going down that domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, there's a whole irony contained in any assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: This unpleasantly arisen experience as a whole, you don't want that pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by not wanting that pain, you go to that which is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that unpleasant... a pleasant... there is an experience, the whole is the experience of sensuality, as we described it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever there is a sense desire, it's first felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't want that unpleasure, you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, how do you think it's going to be felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, like scratching the itch, as it was said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each time you engage, you make it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if you clarify this, you realize that
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality arises, and it's felt unpleasantly, and you don't want pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody wants pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize sensory strength is then the pleasure in regard to that painful sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abstaining from engagement with sensuality is how you're going to free yourself from that pain of that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you want to be free from it, which is why you keep engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sensuality pressures you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's underlined by the pain, simultaneously there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you have any doubt about it, say no to yourself in regard to desire, and you'll see the pressure that builds up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you pressured?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is the... How is that pressure generated?
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure towards sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically, directly corresponds, simultaneously, to the extent of craving that you maintain in regard to the pain that's being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove the craving in regard to the pain, there is no pressure towards the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the prospect of the pleasure of sense objects becomes non-applicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's important, like, I keep going back to this, I don't want to... like, we can talk about it later, about the danger and so on, escape, but it's all contained in first, then you can discern more within the first principle, and that's that any degree of pleasure...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine, actually, physical engagement with sensual pleasure, amidst of physical engagement with sensual pleasure, the pleasurability, pleasurability of physical engagement,
[SPEAKER_01]: ...is actually the delighting in freedom from simultaneously enduring pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not coming from the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's coming from the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: The freedom from that pain, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Alleviation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To whatever extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, it's important to imagine it on the right basis, which is sensuality, sensual engagement, sensual act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure of it, that you experience, that you used to experience, that you sometimes still might want to experience, doesn't matter the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasure is the alleviation of simultaneously enduring pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the pleasure that comes to you through the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It never leaves that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep assuming pleasure to be external.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: to the presently enduring situation that is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: External?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you know... how can you know that this is pleasant while you're not engaging with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pleasure... Again, imagine that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a... there is a prospect of... of sensual, like, touch, of a pleasant nature, but you're not touching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it felt pleasantly, that prospect?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're... if... if the pleasure is in the object of your touch... You're not even touching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you know that it's pleasant now, when you're not touching it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, and again, the argument of, oh, because you have a memory from before,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it still doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are not elated on account of memory.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're elated on account of the future prospect of, I'm about to touch this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, that's felt pleasantly before you touch it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it provides the possibility of the alleviation of this pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the pain is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pain is here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Claiming to get rid of this pain is here, which means prospect that I might be able to is here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whatever pleasure I feel in regard to anything out there, is because of this pain here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that pain is the pain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that pain is the pleasure of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, when you go and engage with things...
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure of sensuality... ...is within that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...comes from that pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't come from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It stays within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the important... That's what I'm trying to... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...to hammer in here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, basically, hammer that in, and there is no basis for assuming external to this experience of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you do assume the sense objects to be external to your experience of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it's insatiable, because you perverted the order, and this domain of sense object
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, you're not even engaging with it, yet you are feeling pleasure on account of the prospect of engaging with, on the level of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a desire there, and that desire is felt like you're delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that desire is fully within this pain, that's simultaneously enduring to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop assuming that then the pleasure of alleviating the pain through following that desire is contained external to the pain and the desire, you will stop perverting the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you stop assuming your sense of self to be outside of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same principle of the same upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing the pleasure as being external to the pain, is basically seeing...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already said it.
[SPEAKER_01]: A thought of pleasure might be external to the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you know that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without engaging with that where the pleasure might be, which you are not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter the extent of your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said before, like when you say, okay, I think I'm outside of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I'm not outside of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something else is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that can only be the thought that's within this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but then there's the outside of that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which can only be within...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same principle in this case, once you start from the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pleasure that's outside of this desire that has arisen, is within this desire that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because how can then you feel it pleasantly, that prospect of that pleasure, unless it's within this desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much all you need to clarify
[SPEAKER_01]: But all the way, and it will become... well, you will become unable to think that pleasure is in sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: The beautiful objects in the world are the ones that have pleasure in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how sensuality falls off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean you... you wouldn't recognize nice food or agreeable touch, but you certainly wouldn't crave for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't crave for gratuitous freedom from unpleasantness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... You don't crave to alleviate by default of anything that's felt discomfortably.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's because that pleasure cannot possibly undo that more fundamental pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always... exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're basically trying to get rid of something by expecting something more particular to get under its roots.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, actually, you... that pain is there whether you like it or not and
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, ironically, you want to be free from it, which is why you engage with centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you need to do is recognize that it's painful first, and you want to be free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, the best course of action, then, is to not engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, that means you now have to be able to endure for as long as it takes, not acting out of the gratuitous assumption of craving in regard to the unpleasant enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, even when you have a thought, a memory of previous sensuality, a thought of the future sensuality, and it's... and the mind delights in it, you don't deny that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just see it as included within this pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that the pleasure that's felt, even if you were to engage, even when you eat the food that's agreeable, the pleasure you're feeling is the alleviation of the simultaneous enduring pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's putting pain first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically... Or not allowing it to be assumed second.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not allowing it to be assumed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not... And it gets assumed second when you... when you become careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're basically not mindful of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the general most... at the general level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or when you lose sense of strength.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that... the past or the future...
[SPEAKER_02]: That's pain right here, right now, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can clarify.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you know that the past prospects were pleasant, unless you're feeling them now pleasurably?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you know that the future prospect of engaging with a particular sense object... Oh, why are you feeling it pleasurably right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the extent, doesn't matter the extent, how particular, how committed to a particular aspect of a sense object that you're deriving pleasure from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any pleasure derived from any sense action is the pleasure of alleviating simultaneously enduring pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the pleasure that comes from the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why you have pressure to engage with the object, is because that's how you give validity to the direction of engagement, which is what alleviates the pain, not gets you the pleasure from the sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no pleasure in the sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just objects of perceptions, which are neither pleasurable nor displeasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you're feeling pleasurable on account of... and as well, that's why people like to pursue central object.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's just given, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's a bit taken away, taken away, taken away, your pleasure grows.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would that happen, if the pleasure were truly in the object?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't touched it yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know that there's more of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, there is more of it in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the desire grows, because the engagement towards that direction grows, because you chose to basically go that way, which means that the... the extent of the prospect of alleviating this also presently enduring pain, grows.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pressure grows, because you, yourself, made it so.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way the Buddha describes the five strands of sensuality, he says it's like sights that you can be conscious of with the eye, that you can be conscious of, that you could be conscious of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Chakravinyaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, it's basically there.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's saying, basically, you are
[SPEAKER_00]: The sensuality is the possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's cakravinyaya in the Pali.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's sights cognized... a big verb to translate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sights cognizable, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cognizable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Vinyaya, which means it could be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's all on the level of possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it already starts there, as soon as you're subjected to pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why also the Buddha said, the only way that Putujana knows out of pain, is through sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is not out of pain, but it's the only way he knows that they would closely resemble to dealing with pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what he thinks will... Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a degree of alleviation.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it weren't so, you wouldn't be pressured by it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's that pursuit, that delight in the possibility of that direction, engaging with it, kind of magically gives the validity of, oh, yes, because I'm doing this, that's why I'm not subjected to this, which you are, obviously, still subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you wouldn't be going down the pursuit, if you're not subjected to the unpleasant desire of it beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the gratification is just seeing that any pleasure you could possibly have is still within.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, as the Buddha said, gratification is on the level of the delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're delighting in the prospect.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have... when you have, like, something secured, you extend, sort of, like, consuming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You prolong it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you just do it, oh, it becomes obvious how it cannot possibly pertain to the domain you're acting from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the extent of your sensual cravings is directly determined by the extent of your craving against the painful feeling that you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any... like when you... and again, as I said, you always start with a... like the... the order you have to start with is the order that's affected with ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't start things rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, okay, yeah, delighting is... essentiality is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, oh, I must stop delighting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not quite a method of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delighting is a symptom of an underlying assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that case, when you are delighting in the prospect of sensuality, you want to then make sure you include the delight and the prospect of sensual pursuit that you're restraining against, but the prospect is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to include the whole thing, including the future sense object, within the container of pain that's presently enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not left, not right, not before, and certainly not after it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that whole assumption that, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a desire, then I engage and I set, like, satisfy the desire, desire runs away.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you... you get tired, basically, from running away from the pain, that then you accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it ceases to hurt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what if you were to accept the pain right away?
[SPEAKER_01]: And removing the middleman of central pursuits that cannot possibly even pertain to the domain of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you realize you'll be above the pain even before the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which... You can't satisfy your desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nobody denies that after a degree of engagement with your sensuality, projected goals of your desires, you don't feel painful anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sense object remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, like you haven't truly consumed it and destroyed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still there, things you've been touching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the food, in a way, it's still there, just now in the stomach, as opposed to the table.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing has come out of the material domain, into you, or got consumed by the all-powerful sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, there is no pain now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you just covered it over.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you cover it over?
[SPEAKER_01]: By... by...
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you cover the door when the domain of senses cannot possibly pertain to the domain of feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: What has changed?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you stop perceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you're not perceiving the pain anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're feeling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What has changed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Pursuing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you stop pursuing it because it doesn't hurt anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it that it doesn't hurt anymore?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did it hurt in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you were just subjected to a painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's not suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Painful feeling is not dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Claiming to be free from painful feeling is what dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the only thing that changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: After a certain amount of engagement with sensual object, pursuit of it in particular, you stopped resisting the unpleasant feeling in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But pursuit of sensual object had nothing
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, exactly, sometimes, if you keep engaging with the pursuit of the sense-objects, it becomes apparent that you cannot do anything to the pain you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: You double down.
[SPEAKER_01]: You triple down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how perception of sense-objects proliferates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it has nothing to do with the domain that you're actually acting from.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, you go to the extremes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to... hoping that some of it will allow your mind to take it as a successful project of diversion, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't know how to stop craving the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just doing these random things, hoping that it will result in you, at least temporarily, forgetting about resisting the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you have to stop engaging with sensuality first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're completely ignorant, you have to start practicing sense restraint first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's basically, it's on the level of a magical belief, a diversion that you know deep down is not... and everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was saying that to Venerable Tanya a while ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I remember even way before, like, when I was in my teens, before I started reading the Buddhism itself, you always knew deep down you can't satisfy your desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: Talking with friends about it, like, you can't say... yeah, you can't help but pursuing them, but you know already you can't satisfy them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only thing that changes, like, before the pursuit and after pursuit, is your own attitude in regard to what you're already feeling, what you've been feeling all along.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you use sense engagement to tire yourself out, so you can't crave the resistance, you can't maintain the resistance towards unpleasantly enduring feeling, and it ceases to be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not suffering, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But habitually, anything disagreeable is resisted, and you make it into suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, many times, and I'm sure everybody experienced that, at some point, even after the culmination of your sensual satisfaction of objects, the mind is still completely unsatisfied, and you want more.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body can't have more.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body's fatigue doesn't... they've each been scratched so much, it hurts, yet, the mental attitude of having their desire completely unchanged, and you're just going mad, basically, with the desire, because you've been giving in to that domain of sense pursuit.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had nothing to do with this, and that's the only way you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so are you saying that when you've kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: You've gone for, sort of, gratifying your desires and then afterwards you feel, sort of, you feel satisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's because, that's basically because, through your acts, you've actually reduced craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I won't say you reduced it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, temporarily... Well, you stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the possibility of craving, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, no, that's true, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Resistance to suffering is craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop resisting when you tire yourself out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, by scratching, I am actually reducing... You are?
[SPEAKER_01]: You are?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's why it is gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how I started this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if there is no gratification, you wouldn't have called it...
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, even the gratification has nothing to do with sense objects, has to do with your own attitude towards your own craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards your own feeling, sorry, which is already an attitude of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, through scratching your itch, you are reducing craving, but simultaneously making your dependence on running away of pain even harder, even stronger, which means, oh, so through reducing this craving, actually, I am fueling more, like, I'll be more subjected to even more craving later on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I need that desire to keep on scratching.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it just fuels itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the only... That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why first you have to stop doing it, and then you realize that even the acts of doing it were rooted in actually, oh, it's simply because I don't want this pain, as in I gratuitously resist it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not painful if I don't resist it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's painful if I resist it and then interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, okay, I gave it validity, next time I'll resist it even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what if I... okay, now I stopped engaging with it, stopped maintaining these wrong avenues of trying to deal with it, stopped scratching my itch.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I now to endure the pain, not act out of it, and then just stop resisting it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if people...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll resist it and then it'll go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like a subha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Subha becomes for people getting rid of the the central pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, yeah, I must resist it so it doesn't bother me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pain is there if it has... if sensuality has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sensuality in its nature is harassing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the nature of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: They harass you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even before your craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The significance, the implications of a female body for a man, or male body for a woman, or food for a hungry person, the implications are forceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even... no effort required.
[SPEAKER_01]: Forceful is felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, automatically, simultaneously, unenlightened mind resists any form of unpleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you experience forceful perceptions, automatically, you're already resisting them, which means, automatically, you're already delighting in them, to get the freedom from this resistance, that you're responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why in Arahant, eh... Aniruddha,
[SPEAKER_01]: When he was... when that woman took him, oh, you can stay in this room, and then came there and took her clothes off, and tried to basically sleep with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the sutta says that he just sat cross-legged and was kind of... became mindful of his breathing, and she was sort of dancing, trying to get his attention, then felt embarrassed, because he wasn't... and then dressed up and apologized.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember the first time I read the sutta, I thought, well, why would Arahant even need to be mindful of his breath?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would he... like, I thought Arahant would be just completely...
[SPEAKER_01]: Blind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, he was aware of the significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that significance is actually harassing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he was mindful of his breath, just because he was subjected to pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because he tried to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, okay, well, this harassment now, until it stops, I'll just sort of be mindful of my experience as a whole, while I'm being tortured.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Rādhāpāla Sutta, when he goes home, already anāgāmī, maybe even an arahant, and the father tells all his wives to dress up provocatively how they used to, how he used to like it, and they go and start trying to seduce him, he says, stop harassing me.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is harassing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like... And it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the nature of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are harassed by your senses being subjected to these forceful sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, like a dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hears something.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't help it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't help it, but he wants to go there now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't need to resist that experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: That level of harassment, doesn't that apply to any at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: It does.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, whether it's painful or pleasant... That's why, if you were to undo the craving on the absolute fundamental level, sensuality would be undone as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot possibly remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, more practically, you might have to address it in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's go back to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything goes... that's the only... that's why I keep saying... the suttas say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things converge in feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not sometimes, not every other day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means your action, your motivation, your perceptions, basically, your moods.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where do they converge?
[SPEAKER_01]: Converge on how you're feeling right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that feeling endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't stop thinking about a central object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does it converge?
[SPEAKER_01]: Converge on presently enduring feeling of discomfort that you're resisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of it, but not by any... by means of distracting yourself in this direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, imagine... well, imagine being really, really hungry, and you eat something not even so tasty, but it provides you this great pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, imagine you're full to the point of feeling sick, and somebody brings something extremely tasty, and you're still sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no pleasure in eating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, if the pleasure were in these sense objects, that wouldn't be the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every time you were to eat a pleasant thing, it would be felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you're hungry, things that were not pleasant, feel pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you're not hungry, things that are pleasant, feel unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's in common to that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's in common to that whatever your senses are subjected to, is in a way forceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It pushes you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Significance implies, requires you, pressures you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, all of that will work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That whole domain of being pressured, implied, pulled, forced upon, will work only if you provide a basis for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the basis is, I resist the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that's how you then become pulled and forced and oppressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop resisting the comfort, none of these things, discomfort, none of these things can possibly enter you, or certainly exercise any influence over you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the assumption, we have assumption is, there's a prospect of pleasure and
[SPEAKER_03]: I can get that, but you're not recognizing the pain where it's coming from.
[SPEAKER_01]: More precisely, the assumption is, assuming the pleasure to be external to the pain, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: External.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: External.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, assuming pleasure to be external to the present enduring pain, that's the assumption of sensuality, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can get rid of it or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already implied, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it's not connected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming being external to the pain, you already form the external relationship between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can say it's before, it's after, it's not connected, it's fully connected, it's the same, it's different, it's both, it's neither, because you already assumed.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, so that it... but basically, it's more that you want that... you assume that that pleasure
[SPEAKER_00]: can get rid of that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's because, more fundamentally, you see it as external from that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you see that that pleasure... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot possibly get rid of that pain, because it... because it isn't separate from that pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always within.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you will stop maintaining the notion of your master controller of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you realize that any notion you can have about it, of sense of self and master and control, it is within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any notion of escape from this presently enduring pain, any notion of pleasure, any thought of, ah, tomorrow I'll experience this, it's within this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at that time, to that extent, that is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why a prospect of going away from it is pleasant at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, again, you don't have to wait tomorrow to say no to yourself in regard to sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can already do it right here, right now, on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sensuality is in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha gave that symbol, like a man lives completely immersed in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a man in the river, drenched, soaked, soaking wet, and then he finds two sticks and he wants to light the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first he needs to step outside of the river, because he can't light the fire with wet sticks.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, even when he's up on the shore, he won't be able to light the fire right away.
[SPEAKER_01]: He needs to wait for sticks to dry, for his hands to dry.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, so it's like the men who... monks who withdraw from sensuality, but their minds are still wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when that dries, then you can... and lighting the fire basically means understanding this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, he can't get wet again, because he's burnt up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, now nothing, you're just kind of generally mindful, you don't have necessarily context of sensual assumptions, and you have a thought of something sensual, that you are about to be subjected to, or could be subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: The delight, the extent of that delight, is the extent of your resistance to pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The extent of that delight is not in the object that you don't have yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: The extent of that delight is the extent of the pain, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, once the skin heals, scratching it, that's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same act of the same centrality, that was felt pleasantly first, because of an underlying condition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you put underlying condition aside, an act of scratching is how... how is it felt then?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, experience of sense objects is always unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're always harassed by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The cow being... whether it leans on the wall, on the tree, sits down, stands, is being consumed by the insect that live in that... on that surface.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is always.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why sensuality, as an attitude, grows.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you engage with it, the more options you get from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's, again, it always stays with you, never, it can never leave that domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no outside of the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, we spoke about it in regard to the phone, but it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're touching something, what are you experiencing?
[SPEAKER_01]: The object you're touching, or you're experiencing the experience of your hand touching something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yet, here you are assuming that pleasure is contained in particular, inside of the particular objects that you can't even enter with your own senses, let alone on the level of the mind, somehow, to kind of transcend this domain and enter this domain of physicality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's inconceivable that it's desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: If I'm maintaining a desire, you're satisfying it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Simultaneous, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then I'm going to satisfy it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm going to keep this thing growing, and it's not going to... it's going to disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but it's going to disappear by becoming more and more apparent, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're getting bigger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you do have... again, as I said, everybody starts from a wrong place first.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you do have a thought of sensual object, don't try to negate it or deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, don't act towards it, which would be overly affirming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, don't try to deny it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how you can discern a context greater than the thought of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is the context created.
[SPEAKER_01]: We just described it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, I... there is again...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm hungry and there is a nice food on the table.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is a delightful prospect.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm practicing restraint, but the delight is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I'm like, oh, I shouldn't feel this, I shouldn't feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, now I still...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, I try to go for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I try to go against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you must stop trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you stop... once you start restraining and don't, as I said, overly affirming to your physical action, you do have to learn how to allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you didn't create it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your only freedom from what you're subjected to is to fully understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't understand it if you keep denying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, food is on the table, I'm very hungry, but I'm restraining myself, it hasn't been offered, I'm not gonna eat it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now I have the delight in my mind, the prospect of eating it, the prospect of somebody coming and offering me, and I'm eating it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you free yourself from that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or how do you regain perspective in regard to that directional prospect?
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, would you be eating the food?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: First of all... Or would you be experiencing your mouth being subjected to food?
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that's the context that you can easily ignore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you realize, if you make an effort to not ignore it, you would actually shift the emphasis from the food, food, food, food, to, oh, these random senses that I was given, subjected to, are then subjected to further things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if those things are agreeable or disagreeable, you stop fearing them, because now you're at the right basis of not being careless in regard to the... As I said, can you experience the food?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you experience any sense object if your senses are not there operating, living?
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no sixth sense base present?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the body is not there functional?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize, it doesn't matter how much I forget this,
[SPEAKER_01]: It is the right order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessity of the six senses comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they're only known through engagement with sense objects, but, again, I cannot abandon them to go to sense objects, because my only formal relationship is within them that relate to sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop assuming external to your six senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, upādāna andhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop assuming external to the sense of five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: ātavādā andhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop assuming external to the basically presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you stop craving against the presently enduring feeling, whether against the words or against the way from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Upādāna, I'm done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's always upādāna.